Guide to the Stanford University, School of Engineering, Dean's Office, Records SC0165
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- General Correspondence, Series 1
  - Sanitary Engineering, 1928-1929 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Memoranda about and model curriculum for Civil Engineering Engineer's Degree in Sanitary Engineering
  - Santa Clara Valley Water Conservation District, 1935-1937 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Correspondence between Dean Morris and engineers at water district about dams; water-related publications; recommendations for registration as civil engineer.
  - Sarson, Evelyn, 1938-1945 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Engineering Secretary, working part-time for the Guggenheim Laboratory. Memoranda about the terms of her appointment and salary amangements.
  - Saville, Thorndike, 1938-1941 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Dean of the College of Engineering at New York University. Correspondence with Dean Morris about engineering facilities at NYU; designation of degrees for engineering graduates; salary data at the two institutions.
  - Schedule Committee, 1925-1926 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    Minutes, agendas, and supporting documents of the School of Engineering committee formed to determine curriculum and normal scheduling of classes to fu1fill BA requirements in engineering.
  - Scherrer, Robert, 1940-1942 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Teaching Assistant; Graduate Student in Civil Engineering. Correspondence with Dean's Office about application for position; financial considerations; appointment.
  - School of Business, 1925-1933 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    Correspondence and memoranda, primarily betrveen Dean Hoover, Willard Hotchkiss (GSB), and President Wilbur about the organization of both schools; procedures for cooperation between them in industrial engineering; scientific business management.
  - School of Education, 1930-1938 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Education and Engineering faculty on topics of mutual interest, such as education students minoring in engineering; educational requirements for various levels of teaching; courses of study for junior-college teachers of engineering.
  - School of Engineering, 1923-1930 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Correspondence, memoranda, minutes and reports dealing with the initial organization of the Engineering School (officiaily established in 1925). Folder includes material on all aspects of school organization, from the earliest proposals through curriculum, graduation requirements, faculty, admininistrative structure.
  - School of Engineering, 1925-1936 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    Memoranda on committee memberships; curriculum. Magazine articles written by Dean Hoover about the school; other publicity information.
  - School of Engineering: Graduate Phase, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    When the School of Engineering was created, attention was first devoted to designing undergraduate curriculum. (see preceding folder). In 1926, the graduate phase of engineering education was examined, and policies set for curriculum, advanced degree requirements, and the faculty and facilities necessary for the program. Folder consissts of memoranda and reports on these topics.
  - School of Engineering: Limitation of Enrollment, 1926-1930 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    Memoranda proposing various methods of controlling enrollment in the upper division of the Engineering School.
  - School of Engineering: Office Change, 1941-1942 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    Memoranda about renovation and changes needed in Engineering Corner.
  - Schuette, Evan Henry, 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    Applications and letters of recommendation for graduate fellowship.
  - Scobey, Fred, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    Chairman of the Research Committee of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Correspondence with Dean Morris about publications offered to Stanford; ASCE membership.
  - Seismological Society of America, 1930-1959 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    Correspondence on various topics related to earthquake research, including the west coast visit of Japanese earthquake specialist Professor Suyehiro; election of Society officers; Dean Morris' election to Board of Directors; development of earthquake research in California.
  - Seismological Station, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    Memoranda by Dean Hoover, Sidney Townley and Robert Swain about the encroachment of the Stanford golf course on the Branner Seisrnometer Station research area.
  - Shattuck, George, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    Correspondence about his eligibility for an Engineer's degree in Civil Engineering.
  - Shoemaker, R. W. and Benjamin, 1938-1944 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    Correspondence between the Shoemakers and Dean Morris on vibration testing of wires; letters of introduction; legal case involving copper stock; high school curriculum; electrical wiring.
  - Shoup, Paul, 1928, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    Vice-Chairman of the Southern Pacific Railroad. Folder concerns employment of college graduaes in the railroads. (See also "Railroad Engineering" folder.)
  - Shulits, Samuel, 1937-1939 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    Professor at Colorado School of Mines. Applied unsuccessfully for teaching position at Stanford. Correspondence, letters of recommendation, and reprints of his publications in support of his application.
  - Sievert, Walter, 1935-1941 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    Colleague of Dean Morris at Pasadena Water Department. Correspondence about Morris Dam; Pasadena water projects; publications, and other areas of personal and professional interest.
  - Sigma Xi, 1927-1941 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    Correspondence and memoranda about applications for Sigma Xi nembership; information about meetings, and other Society events.
  - Sigma Xi, 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Skilling, Hugh Hildreth, 1928-1941 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    Professor of Electrical Engineering, Chairman of E.E. Department, Acting Dean in absence of Dean Terman. Memoranda about appointment, promotions, professional activities.
  - Skinker, Thomas, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    Civil Engineer in Saint Louis and President of Engineer's Club of St. Louis. Conespondence with Dean Morris about Club, and invitation for Morris to speak there.
  - Slides, 1936-1939, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    Correspondence between Dean Morris and various engineering companies and public works about borrowing and lending slides of utilities projects.
  - Smith, Wayne, 1939-1943 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    Graduate student, teaching assistant, acting instructor. Correspondence with Dean Morris about his application to Stanford; appointments; draft deferment; post-Stanford life.
  - Snow Conference, 1941-1944 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    Informational material sent to Dean Morris by Western Snow Confererence about meetings, snow depth, and reservoir storage.
  - Social Sciences, School of, 1932, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    Memoranda of 1932 concerned with reorganizing Graduate Study Committee; 1946 report on Liberal Arts program at Stanford.
  - Society of Automotive Engineers, 1935-1941 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    News releases; questionnaire regarding automotive engineering courses available at Stanford.
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1920-1930 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    Group formed to evaluate all fields in college engineering education to develop general standards, and to apply these standards in accreditating curriculum at various institutions. Folder contains informational material on goals of organization; meetings; committee appointments. Correspondence rvith Dean Hoover from SPEE officers; responses to questionnaire sent by Hoover to engineering alumni about the quality of their engineering education.
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1931-1935 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1937-1939 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1940-1942 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1943-1946 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, Committees, 1940-1942 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Dean Morris was a member of the S.P.E.E. development and placement committee. Correspondence about committee appointments; activities of various S.P.E.E. committees; reports of committees.
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, Converntion in Berkeley, 1937-1940 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    Correspondence related to the plan of having S.P.E.E.'s 1939 meeting co-hosted by Stanford and Berkeley, and held at Stanford. Difficulties related to housing and supplies developed, so meeting was actually held at Berkeley in 1940.
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, Pacific Southwest Section, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    Correspondence between Herbert Wheaton, chairman of the S.P.E.E. program committee, and Dean Morris, about Morris presiding over one of the sessions at the S.P.E.E. Pacific Southwest Section annual meeting in 1941.
  - Soil Conservation, 1938-1942 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    Correspondence between Dean Morris and officials of the Soil Conservation Service of the USDA about employment of student assistants for summer work with SCS; Publications of the Service of interest to Stanford.
  - Sonderegger, A. L., 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    Consulting Engineer in Los Angeles. Correspondence with Dean Morris about hydrology, and civil engineering education.
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    This folder, and the following eight folders, are concerned with a major fund-raising drive to construct a new Space Sciences Building. Correspondence and memoranda on estimated space, equipment, and financial needs; strategies for fund-raising approaches both to governmental agencies and private enterprises; proposals submitted to NASA and various aeronautics corporations; memoranda of discussions with potential donors; GSO's estimates of corporate donor profiles.
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1965 Jan-May (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1965 Jun-Dec (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1966 Jan-May (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1966 Jun-Dec (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1967 Jan-May (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, 1967 Jun-Dec (Box 8, Folder 5)
    In addition to topics discussed in previous folders, this folder contains information pertaining to ground-breaking ceremony; invitations to ceremony, and responses to invitations.
  - Space Engineering and Science Building: Gift Projections, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    "Corporation worksheets" prepared on various potential corporate donors, including names and alma maters of executives, stock holdings, financial data and gift histories.
  - Space Engineering and Science Building, Proposal to NASA, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Speakers' Bureau, 1936-1944 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    A.S.S.U. bureau that provided Stanford student speakers to address community groups on their fields of expertise. Folder consists of requests for student speakers from Engineering School, and surveys of engineering faculty members to determine best student speakers.
  - Stalnaker, John M., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Dean of Students. Memoranda to Stalnaker from H.H. Skilling and F.E. Terman about admissions criteria; married student housing.
  - Standard Oil Company, 1929, 1936-1944 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Correspondence between Dean's Office and Standard Oil officials about employment possibilities for Stanford graduates; curriculum; Standard's request for an engineer with sand-dune experience.
  - Standard Oil Fellowships, 1938-1943 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Information about and applications for Standard Oil Fellowships, availab1e to engineering graduate students.
  - Stanford-Lane Hospital Power Plant, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Report by A.L. London of Mechanical Engineering on equipment and operations of Hospital power plant.
  - Stanford Research Institute, Relations with, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Correspondence and memoranda dealing with difficulties between SRI and Stanford University on questionsof administrative authority and fundraising policies.
  - Stanford-Sperry Agreement, 1938-1945 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    This folder and the three following folders contain correspondence, memoranda and legal documents involving patents on the klystron and its various components; licensing agreements entered into by Stanford University and the Sperry Gyroscope Company for manufacture and distribution of klystron; and miscellanceous legal and financial details.
  - Stanford-Sperry Agreement, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Similar contents to preceding folder, but also includes material on agreement worked out between Sperry and several Electrical Engineering professors, particularly F.E. Terman, for electronics inventions.
  - Stanford-Sperry Agreement, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Starford-Sperry Agreement, 1952-1956 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Stanford University Press, 1933-1946 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    Correspondence between editors at Stanford Press and Dean's Office soliciting opinions on submitted manuscripts; recommendations about funds to be appropriated for publishing certain works; minutes of S.U. Press faculty committee offering recommendations on several book proposals.
  - Statistics, Committee on Instruction in, 1939-1946 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Minutes and supporting documentation of a faculty committee composed of instructors from various departments investigating the use of statistical methods in the University.
  - Stockman, Jay, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Patent attorney representing David Willard, inventor of the Willard Automatic Volume Control. Correspondence between Stockman and Dean Morris attempting to arrange a developnent and licensing agreement between Willard and the University.
  - Structural Engineering, 1929, 1936-1945 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    Correspondence between the Structural Engineers' Association of Northern California and Dean Morris about the Association's meetings and activities; report concerning proposed two-year graduate curriculum in Structural Engineering for degree of Engineer in Civil Engineering.
  - Student Costs and Income Statistics, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    Tabulations and graphs compiled by Stanford Controller Kenneth Creighton about income per student and operating expenditures per student.
  - Student Engineer's Council, 1927-1930 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    Correspondence with Dean Hoover related to student chapters at Stanford of several national engineering groups, such as S.P.E.E., A.I.E.E., etc.
  - Sullivan, Alice, 1937-1944 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    Secretary in the School of Engineering. Memoranda about appointment, reappointrnent, changes in salary and status.
  - Summer Quarter, 1940-1945 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    Memoranda about budgeting and staff needs for summer quarter instruction; appointments; scheduling. Correspondence with high school principals and junior college administrators about summer programs. (See also "Four-Quarter Engineering Committee" folder.)
  - S - general correspondence, 1921-1930 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - S - general correspondence, 1931-1936 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - S - general correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - S - general correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - S - general correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - S - general correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - S - general correspondence, 1950-1955 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Tau Beta Pi, 1932-1937 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Correspondence related to the establishment of Tau Beta Pi chapter at Stanford in 1935. Constitution and bylaws of Stanford Chapter. Information on activities and elections. Copy of Tau Beta Pi entrance exaimination.
  - Tau Beta Pi, 1938-1944 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Lists of students, faculty, and alumni eligible for election to society; information on activities, membership and officers; applications and recommendations for Tau Beta Pi Fellowships.
  - Taylor Howard S., 1928-1935 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Instructor in Mining and Metallurgy. Correspondence about his receiving engineering degree at University of Michigan under special circumstances; appointments to Stanford; reconmendations for civi1 service positions.
  - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1935-1936 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between Dean Morris and Carl Bock (engineer for the TVA) and Mr. Sturdevant (TVA Director of Information) about TVA technical publications and information; offer of position as Chief Design Engineer to Morris; cement crack problems in dams.
  - Terman, Frederick E., 1927, 1931-1937, 1940-1942 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Stanford alumnus, professor, and later Executive Head of the Electrical Engineering Department; Dean of Engineering; University Provost. Correspondence between Terman and the Dean's Office about his publications; equipment, budget and staff needs in the Communications Laboratory; recommendations to Dean Morris about various E.E. faculty members.
  - Terman, Frederick E., 1942-1945 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Correspondence between Hugh Skilling, Dean Morris and Terman, when the latter was in Cambridge as the Director of the Harvard Radio Research Laboratory.
  - Terman, Frederick E., 1960-1963 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Biographical and bibliographic information; corrrespondence about his nominations for the I.R.E. Founderrs Award, and the A.I.E.E. Edison Medal, both of which he was awarded.
  - Terman Engineering Award, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Award given to top 5% of seniors in Electrical Engineering. Students were given a monetary prize, and honored at a luncheon to which the high school teacher each winner cited as most influential in his academic development was also invited. Folder contains correspondence with students, parents, designated high school teachers, and advisors. on subjects reLated to the award and ceremony.
  - Terman Engineering Award, 1967-1969 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Terman Engineering Award, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Terman Engineering Award, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Terman Engineering Fund, 1950-1961 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Memoranda concerning gifts made by Terman to the Engineering School, and the allocation of these funds.
  - Terzaghi, Karl, 1935-1936 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    International soil expert; Professor at Technische Hochschule, Vienna. Correspondence about his planned visit to the United States; invitation to give series of lectures at Stanford; related arrangements for travel, scheduling.
  - Testing Machine and Laboratory, 1929-1939 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Memoranda aboutmetal-testing machinery in School of Engineering; inventory of existing machinery and requests for new machinery; disposal of outmoded apparatus; purchase of new equipnent; mechanical problems.
  - Textbooks, School of Engineering, 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Lists compiled by Engineering School faculty members of the textbooks used in their classes.
  - Thomas, Carl, 1936-1938 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Stanford engineering alumnus and friend of Dean Morris. Correspondence between Morris and Thomas on alumnia activities and professional interests.
  - Thomas, Earl, 1930-1945 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Professor of Civil Engineering. Correspondence and memoranda about travel expenses; Stanford facilities for materials testing; traffic engineering; promotions.
  - Thomas, Franklin, 1935-1944 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    Professor of Civil Engineering at California Institute of Technology; personal friend of Dean Morris. Correspondence with Morris on various personal and professional topics, including Pasadena water system; membership in engineering societies; ASCE visit to Colorado River Aqueduct, etc.
  - Thompson, Milton, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Professor of Aeronautics at the University of Michigan. Offered position at Stanford by Dean Morris, but declined job on financial grounds. Correspondence related to his qualifications for position; information on appointment and rejection of offer.
  - Three-Year Plan, 1936-1939 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Three-year program entered following completion of lower division that would lead to the MA degree. This was intended to replace the normal four-year AB degree program. Dean Morris was appointed member of this committee by President Wilbur. Folder consists of memoranda and reports on various aspects of such a program.
  - Three-Year Plan Committee, 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Supporting documents of this committee.
  - Tickell, Frederick E., 1936-1945 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    Professor and Executive Head of Mining Engineering. Correspondence with Dean's Office about his appointment; department business. Report by Tickell on the state of the Mining Engineering Department at Stanford.
  - Tiltmeter, 1933-1936 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Correspondence about two instruments at Stanford that measured inclinations of the earth's surface for seismic research. One Tiltmeter was donated to Stanford; the other was on loan from Bureau of Standards. Information and specifications for these devices; correspondence about their use; terms of loan.
  - Tipton, Boyce, 1940-1943 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    Consulting Civil Engineer; friend of Dean Morris. Holiday correspondence with Morris; letter about Tipton's membership on A.S.C.E. committees.
  - Todd, Oliver, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    Consulting Engineer; specialist in flood control. Correspondence with Dean Morris and Abel Wolman of the National Resources Planning Board about possible employrnent. Includes Todd's bibliography, curriculum vita, and statement of qualifications.
  - Townley, Sidney D., 1925-1931, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    Professor of Mathematics at Stanford. Correspondnece with Dean's Office about astronomy, geodesy, and seismology, particularly as related to earthquake research.
  - Turkish Students, 1938-1944 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    The Turkish government sent several Turkish students to study engineering at Stanford at this time. Correspondence with the Dean's Office from the Institute of International Education and Turkish educational officials deals with the admissions, activities, expenses, and academic records of these students.
  - T - general correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - T - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    Correspondence between Dean Morris and the Commissioner of the Bureau (first John Page, later H.N. Bashore)about Stanford's participation in Bureau research; Page's resignation as Commissioner; U.S.B.R. publications.
  - U.S. Public Health Service, 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    Correspondence between Arthur Miller Sanitary Engineer in charge of the U.S.P.H. and Dean Morris about undergraduate and graduate curriculum in Sanitary Engineering at Stanford.
  - Universities: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1940-1946 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    Correspondence between Dean's Office and faculty members at various other universities on topics related to engineering education.
  - Universities: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Universities: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - U - general correspondence, 1925-1933 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - U - general correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - U - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Veteran's Committee - Engineering, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    In 1945, President D.B. Tresidder sent a form letter to all Stanford men in the armed forces to determine how many planned to return to Stanford, and what their educational and housing needs would be after their return from service. In this folder are copies of all such correspondence with engineering students.
  - Vibration Research, 1926-1929 (Box 9, Folder 39)